Okay, let's look at this data value of
type Connection that we had on the slides,
and where I promised that I would
show how it corresponds to a Tree.
How this could be thought of as being such.
And of course, actually, the
illustration is very simple.
It's very similar to how I previously
have depicted other expressions.
Because it's also just an expression
where the functions are now not
'colored' and 'translated' and other things that
I used when I talked about Picture expressions.
But now these are data constructors,
which are also functions.
So, how is this to be interpreted?
So, we have something which is constructed
with this Train data constructor.
So, as a Tree, the Train would be the thing which
appears at the root of the Node of the Tree.
And we know that it has three arguments.
We know this both from the expression as we see
here, but also from the datatype definitions.
So, that means there are three arguments.
So, in this expression,
illustration, three subtrees.
And the first one is this
path, this expression,
which, in turn, is Day
applied to three arguments.
So, at this position in the tree we would
have this label/constructor/tag name 'Day'.
Below that, we have three
arguments, which are three integers.
So, they are simply constants
which appear in the Tree here.
Then we have the second argument, the second
subtree of Train, which is of this form.
So, it's our constructor, and the argument 11.
And, similarly, for the last thing.
Okay, and then in that way, of course, any
value of type 'Connection' can be depicted.
And if it would be a 'Flight' Connection,
then at the root here we would have a Flight.
And it would have a different
number of arguments.
And also, the role would be different.
So, the first argument would
be a string, etc.
So, but it will still be a Tree
that we can easily interpret.
Okay, so this is how this is drawn as a Tree.
And then I also talked about on the
next slide, the computation, how it is.
I promised that this would also be explained.
And for this, we can simply get this code here.
And, well, let's make this a bit
bigger also to see what's going on.
Okay, so let's assume that we
wanted to apply this travelTime
function to exactly this
value that we have up here.
Then what has to happen?
Well, you first have to decide
which of the two equations to use.
But that's, of course, not very difficult.
Right?
We have two equations.
One for trains and one for flights.
And only one of them applies.
And it doesn't really matter in which order.
Even if this would be the first equation
about flight, it would not match.
Because we have a Train value actually at
the root here of this complete argument.
So, in any case, you would always
end up using this equation here.
Okay, and then how is this used?
Well, let's see.
Basically, by checking: we have Train.
So, that's this Train.
Then there is an anonymous variable.
So, we don't care about the first argument here.
Because this is not relevant for
computing the travel time in hours.
It doesn't matter, according to our
definition, which days this happens on.
So, then that's why we don't use this part.
Or we don't do anything with it.
Then the second argument must
be an Hour of something.
Well, that's exactly what happens here.
And well, this Hour in the
concrete example is 11, of course.
And in the function definition, the
variable (named 'd') is used for that,
which tells us that we will bind this to
the variable ('d') for the right-hand side.
Then something similar happens, of course,
with the last argument, so this is the
third argument of Train and it is an Hour.
And this, of course, matches with this Hour.
So, we have now matched
against this and against this.
And then this tells us that this deeper
argument, so what we have here, is the ('a').
Okay, for that first thing, it would
be a ('d') and this is an ('a').
Okay.
And then we have matched
the whole left-hand side.
Yes, we have found out that this actually matches
or this is applicable to the
value that we have been given.
That means that we should use the
right-hand side of exactly this equation.
And the right-hand side says: a minus d plus one.
And of course, this is the
same as 14 minus 11 plus one,
we now know. And this is the same as 4.
So, travelTime applied to this value,
to this data value will result in
the computation in the integer form.
That's it,
how this pattern-matching
and this computation works.
And that's how it works for all datatypes.
No matter how they are defined.
The compiler checks that patterns that are used
here actually make sense according to the type.
The input type of the function and, of course,
the datatype definition that
was given for Connections.
So, we can't somehow, for example, completely
forget about this anonymous variable.
If you don't write this, then the compiler
will complain, even before computing anything,
that this doesn't make sense.
Because Train takes three arguments according
to the type definition, not just two.
Right?
And in that sense, everything works together
and leads to meaningful computation at runtime.